here's my favorite diagram for finding
the sum of the first n squares imagine a
stack of squares is pictured here we see
one squared plus 2 squared plus 3
squared and so on up to N squared where
in this case we've pictured n equals 4.
now we create a tower using the L-shaped
gnomons we have one row with two n minus
one squares two rows with two n minus
three squares and so on all the way down
until we have n rows of one square then
we can use one stack of the sum of the
first n squares on the left side like
this and we can use another stack of the
sum of the first n squares on the right
side of the tower like this to create a
rectangular diagram we've used three
copies of the sum of the squares to
create this rectangular diagram which
has a width of two n plus one and a
length of the sum of the first n
positive integers so three times the sum
of the first n positive squares is equal
to the sum of the first n positive
integers times two n plus one we apply
the formula for the sum of the first n
positive integers to see that the sum of
the first n squares is n times n plus 1
times 2N plus one divided by six